Finding Aid for the Susie Daniel Kirtland Green Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Susie Daniel Kirtland Green Collection
2012
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0180
1.68 linear_feet
Mrs. Susie Daniel Kirtland Green (1887-1967), an associate of Margaret Sanger, operated the first birth control clinic in Tennessee at 2204 21st Avenue, South, Nashville, Tennessee, from 1932 to about 1941. In 1941 she began to sell Fem-A-Gyn contraceptive suppositories, which she developed from a recipe that Margaret Sanger included in her “Family Limitation” pamphlet. She and her daughter, Ruth H. Mocker continued a modestly successful mail order business until 1970.
The collection documents Green's professional life as a birth control advocate.
For more information on Susie Daniel Kirtland Green and birth control in Tennessee see article “Class, Controversy, and Contraceptives: Birth Control Advocacy in Nashville, 1932-1944” by William B. Turner in Tennessee Historical Quarterly. Fall, 1994.
The patient records series, which span 1934 to 1966 are restricted.
The Susie Daniel Kirtland Green Collection was deposited in Special Collections by her daughter Ruth H. Mocker.
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing 1948-1962 (3) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incoming –Client Anonymous-Currey (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Incoming –Client Danner-Jones (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Incoming –Client Lee-Odle (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Incoming –Client Park-Summers (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Incoming –Client Tate-Z, fragments (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Incoming –Business Food and Drug Administration (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Incoming –Business Legal (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Incoming –Business Tennessee Department of Revenue (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Personal
  - Prayers, Poems, and Testamonials (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Datebook, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notes –Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Fem-A-Gyn Tablets
  - Copy of the Federal Trademark Certificate for Fem-A-Gyn (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Invoice for the Manufacture of the Fem-A-Gyn Tablets (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Direction and Content Labels for tablets (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Draft of Brochure for Fem-A-Gyn Tablets (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Photographs
  - Susie D. K. Green and the TN Birth Control Bureau (2) (Box 1, Folder 17)
    TN Birth Control Bureau (2)
    Susie D. K. Green photograph and negative
    Susie D. K. Green, Margaret Sanger, Dr. Hanna Stone –Washington D.C.
    1934 photograph and 2 negatives
  - Margaret Sanger Clinic, NYC 1934 (6) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Susie D. K. Green on steps of Margaret Sanger Clinic, NYC 1934
    Susie D. K. Green with doctor and nurses at African-American birth
    control clinic, NYC (3)
  - Children of patients (6) (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Writings by Susie D. Kirtland Green
  - Holograph articles by Susie d. Kirtland Green (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Tennessee Birth Control Bureau
  - Pamphlets for the Tennessee Birth Control Bureau (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Copy of article in Birth Control Review on the Tennessee Birth Control Bureau in Nashville, TN (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Stationery from the Tennessee Birth Control Bureau (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Pictoral Chart of Pregnancy –15 views (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Anatomical and Gynecological Chart –Tennessee Birth Control Bureau (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Newspaper Clippings
  - Birth Control and Overpopulation –1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Birth Control and Overpopulation –1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Birth Control and Overpopulation –1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Birth Control and Overpopulation –1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Unwanted Babies (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Birth Control and Overpopulation –no date (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Clippings –Binder (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Obituary of Margaret Sanger, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Publications by Others
  - “Human Sterilization Today” (2) by the Human Betterment Foundation, “Table of Sterilizations Done in U.S. up to January 1, 1942” by the Human Betterment Foundation “Effects of Eugenic Sterilization as Practices in California” (2) by the Human Betterment Foundation (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - “Why Desegregation Will Fail” (2) by Leon C. Burns (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - “In Memory of Susannah Gifford, 1854-1925” by Walter E. Dewey (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - “Dew-e-Way Douche Pamphlet” (2) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - “How to use a Feminine Syringe” by B. F. Goodrich Company (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - “In Memoriam: James Freyer Cooper” by S. Adolphus Knopf (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - “The Population Bomb” by the Hugh Moore fund (3) (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Library Guide –New York State Nurses Association (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Planned Parenthood Association of Nashville –1978 Annual Report (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - “Family Limitation” 12th and 17th editions by Margaret Sanger (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - “Woman, Mortality, and Birth Control” by Margaret Sanger (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Flyer for Margaret Sanger autobiography (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - “Twenty Years” by the Margaret Sanger Research Bureau (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Artifacts
  - Ticket -American Conference on Birth Control and National Recovery –1934 (Box 3)
  - Douche nozzles (2) (Box 3)
    Dainty Maid
    Dew-E-Way
  - Ourex Teaching Diaphragm (Box 3)
  - D. C. Gynecological mannequin –teaching diaphragm (Box 3)
- RESTRICTED